Guide to the Records of the Washington Square Music Festival MC.158
New York University Archives
Records of the Washington Square Music Festival
1953-2019
New York University Archives
Campbell, Margaret T.
Washington Square Music Festival
Friedman, Margaret
MC.158
11.7 Linear Feet in 4 record cartons, 7 manuscript boxes, 3 flat boxes, and 1 card box
91 Gigabytes
1 videocassettes (vhs)
1 videocassettes (vhs-c)
14 audiocassettes
5 videocassettes (video 8)
The Records of the Washington Square Music Festival are comprised of the administrative files of the Washington Square Music Festival, a nonprofit group supporting public concerts in Washington Square Park, which operated under the auspices of the Washington Square Association. The files include information about the organization's finances and development, as well as the musicians and concerts it hosted, scrapbooks, photographic materials (photographs, negatives, and contact sheets), and audio-visual materials (audiocassettes, VHS cassettes, CDs, and DVDs) mostly of performances during the festival.
Access Restrictions
Access to some materials may be restricted. Contact the New York University Archives for further information.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Original donation received June 2001; the accession number associated with this donation is 01.005. 2022 accretion donated by Peggy Friedman, Executive Director, Washington Square Music Festival, November 2022. The accession number associated with the accretion is 2022.091.
Arrangement Note
Series I of this collection is arranged alphabetically by folder title in one series. All original folder titles have been retained; additions appear in brackets where clarification is necessary.
The 2022 accretion has not been arranged by an archivist. The materials are arranged in the order in which they were received from the donor.
History of the Washington Square Music Festival
The Washington Square Music Festival was founded in 1953 by violinist Alexander Schneider and the Washington Square Association. The Washington Square Music Festival is a tax-exempt 501(c)(3) nonprofit organization, which operates specifically to provide free public concerts in Washington Square Park. It is sponsored by the Washington Square Association, a civic group formed in 1906, and is funded in part by the affiliated nonprofit Washington Square Association Music Fund. Since the 1970s, the Festival and its fundraising activities have been largely overseen by Executive Director Margaret "Peggy" Friedman and Chairperson Margaret T. "Peggy" Campbell. Friedman remains Executive Director today.
Past performances have included works by diverse composers, including Leonard Bernstein and Richard Wagner, as well as works for the band and chamber ensemble. Planned programming for 2012 will also include a West African concert. The Festival has hosted a number of conductors, ensembles, and soloists, including longtime oboist and conductor Henry Schuman.
The Washington Square Music Festival continues to hold events each summer.
Sources:
"A History of the Washington Square Music Festival," circa 1980; Records of the Washington Square Music Festival; MC 158; Box 2; Folder 44; New York University Archives.
"Initiatives: Music and Concerts: Washington Square Music Festival," Washington Square Association, Accessed April 11, 2012, http://www.washingtonsquarenyc.org/washington_square_music_festival.htm.
Letter from Gilbert DiLucia to residents of Greenwich Village, May 11, 1984; Records of the Washington Square Music Festival; MC 158; Box 2; Folder 20; New York University Archives.
"Washington Square Music Festival's 54th Season," Washington Square Music Festival, Accessed April 11, 2012, http://www.washingtonsquaremusicfestival.org/pages/program.html?ID=3222.
Born-Digital Access Policies and Procedures
Born-digital materials have not been transferred and may not be available to researchers. Researchers may request access copies. To request that material be transferred, or if you are unsure if material has been transferred, please contact New York University Archives, special.collections@nyu.edu, 212-998-259] with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact New York University Archives, special.collections@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596, with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Related Materials at the New York University Archives
Records of the Washington Square Association, Inc. (MC 94)
Ruth Wittenberg Papers (MC 95)
Washington Square Park (New York, N.Y.) and Washington Square Area Image Collection (NYU.ARCH.PHOTO.00001)
Scope and Content Note
This collection is comprised of the administrative records of the Washington Square Music Festival. It includes files on grant applications, development campaigns, and budget reports, as well as the correspondence of the organization's chairman, coordinator, and executive director. Additionally, there is some correspondence from the early period of the Music Festival between members of the public and members of the Washington Square Association, especially H. Stanley Hillyer (chairman of the Concert Committee) and Association secretary Elsa Gray Steinert.
The collection also documents the planning of Festival concerts held in Washington Square Park and other Greenwich Village locations, including press releases and clippings, correspondence with musicians and conductors, drafts of programs, musical and equipment selections, and promotional material.
The 2022 accretion to the Records of the Washington Square Music Festival (1953-2019) include some administrative records, correspondence, performance programs, citations and proclamations from the City of New York, scrapbooks, photographic materials (photographs, negatives, and contact sheets), and audio-visual materials (audiocassettes, VHS cassettes, CDs, and DVDs) mostly of performances during the festival.
Washington Square (New York, N.Y.); Music.; Musical performance.; Musicians.; Administrative records; Correspondence.; Festivals.; Greenwich Village (New York, N.Y.); Washington Square Association Music Fund; Washington Square Association
- Series I
  - Advertisements, 1954-1976 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - After Dinner Opera Company - "Buxom Joan", 1975-1976 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Benefit 1976 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Benefit 1977 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Benefit 1978 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Benefit 1979 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Benefit 1980 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Benefit 1981 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Benefit 1982, 1979-1982 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Benefit 1983 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Benefit 1984 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Benefit 1985 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Benefit 1992-1993 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Benefit 1994 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Benefit 1995 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - [Bloom, Arthur (Conductor)], circa 1974-1976 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - [Bogin, Abba (Pianist)], 1985-1988 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Bookkeeping 1975, 1973-1975 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Bookkeeping 1976 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Budgets 1989, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - [Buketoff, Igor], circa 1970s (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - [Bychkov, Semyon], 1978 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Chairperson's Letters 1975, 1974-1975 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Chairperson's Letters 1976 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Chairperson's Letters 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Chairperson's Letters 1978-1983 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Children's Events, 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Citibank - Music Fund Account and Funding, 1953-1985 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Clippings, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Clippings, 1957-1958 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Clippings, 1960-1963 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - [Clippings, Correspondence, and Reports], 1953-1980 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Comments on Concerts, 1953-1954 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - [Community Board #2], 1980-1984 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Concert Folders [Promotional Materials], 1954-1959 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Concerts, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Concerts (1 of 2), 1955 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Concerts (2 of 2), 1955 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Concerts [Clippings], undated, 1960-1967 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Contracts and Insurance, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - [Contreras, Jose], 1978-1979 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Cooper Union, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Coordinator's Letters, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Coordinator's Letters, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - [Darden, Charles], 1978-1984 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - [Department of] Cultural Affairs, 1976-1978 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Department of Cultural Affairs, 1977-1979 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Department of Cultural Affairs, 1980-1984 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Department of Cultural Affairs, 1993-1994 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - [De Tar, Vernon (choirmaster, organist) and Schuman, Henry (oboist, conductor)], 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Director's Letters, 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Director's Letters, 1977-1979 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Director's Letters, 1979-1985 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - [Dunkel, Paul], 1977-1984 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Endowment [National Endowment for the Arts], 1959-1978 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Equipment, circa 1984 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - [Estrin, Harvey], 1977-1981 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - [Executive] Director's Correspondence, 1983-1985 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Fact Sheets and Information, circa 1972-1980 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Foundations, 1973-1975 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Foundations [and] Fundraising, 1974-1978 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - [Frazor, Terence (conductor)], 1972-1974 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Funding Ideas, 1982-1985 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Fundraising, 1977-1979 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Fundraising, 1981-1982 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Fundraising, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Fundraising, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Fundraising, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Fundraising Information, 1981-1983 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - [Gilbert, David], 1983 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Grant Applications, 1990-1994 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - [Grossman, Herb], 1977 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - "In Memory of..." Concert Donations, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - IRS Financial Forms, 1984-1991 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - [Jenkins, Newell], 1979-1985 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - [Jenkins, Newell and Davis, Douglas], 1972-1976 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - [Kaiser, Amy], 1982-1983 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Letters of Appreciation, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - [Manahan, George], circa 1970s (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - [Maull, George Marriner], 1973-1980 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - [Michalak, Thomas], 1985 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Music Performance Trust Fund [American Federation of Musicians] Local 802, 1975-1985 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - National Endowment for the Arts, 1976-1978 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Natural Heritage Trust, 1993-1995 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - New School for Social Research, 1976-1982 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - New York State Council on the Arts, 1974-1975 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - New York State Council on the Arts, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - New York State Council on the Arts, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - New York State Council on the Arts, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - New York State Council on the Arts, 1981-1983 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - New York State Council on the Arts, 1984-1985 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - New York State Council on the Arts, 1991-1993 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - New York University, 1973-1977 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - New York University, 1978-1985 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Paid Bills, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Paid Bills, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Paid Bills, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Paid Bills, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Paid Bills, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Paid Bills, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Paid and Unpaid Bills, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Paid and Unpaid Bills, undated (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Paid Check Notices, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Panama Francis and the Savoy Sultans, 1993-1994 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Parks, 1954-1986 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - [Parks and Cultural Affairs], 1975 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Plans for Concerts, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Press [Clippings], 1986 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Press [Clippings], 1988 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Press [Clippings], 1989 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Press Releases, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Program Contracts [Department of Cultural Affairs], 1991-1992 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Programs, 1953-1966 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Programs, 1967-1979 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Programs, 1980-1987 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Programs, 1988-1997 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Programs, 1998-2000 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Publicity, 1971-1975 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Publicity, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Publicity, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Publicity, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Publicity, 1979-1981 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Publicity, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Publicity, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Publicity, 1984-1985 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Rain Policy - Insurance, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Receipts, 1971-1977 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Research - [American] Music, 1972-1976 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - [Rikko, Fritz (conductor)], 1973-1977 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Salute to Kansas City - McGlaughlin, 1989-1990 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - [Schuman, Henry (conductor)], 1973-1978 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - [Schuman, Henry (conductor)], 1979-1988 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - [Schwarz, Gerard (conductor)], 1977 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - [Somary, Johannes], 1974-1985 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - [Stein, Andrew (Borough President)], 1974-1980 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Tax Changes, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Taxes, 1969-1975 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Tax Papers, 1955-1973 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Tax Paperwork and Budget, 1959-1984 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - [Tunicka, Maria], 1980-1981 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Vincent [Astor] Foundation, 1981-1982 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - [Weisberg, Arthur (conductor)], 1976 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Unprocessed restricted items pulled from other boxes (Box 4)